Arthur Jacobs

Curriculum Vitae

⊠ asjacobs@inf.ufrgs.br https://asjacobs92.github.io/ Male, Brazilian, born on 10/Sep/1992.

Fourth year PhD student in Computer Science, in the Federal University of Rio Grande do Sul, advised by Prof. Dr. Lisandro Granville, and co-advised by Prof. Dr. Ronaldo Ferreira. Currently visiting Princeton University, under the supervision of Prof. Dr. Jennifer Rexford, and working closely with Dr. Walter Willinger, from NIKSUN. Passionate about science and development, with a strong will to learn about a multitude of subjects, and to build impacting and complex projects. Research interests include network management, Network Functions Virtualization, Intent-based Networking, Natural Language Processing for network management, self-driving networks, programmable networks and artificial intelligence.

Education

Sep 2019 - Jul 2020 **Princeton University**, Visiting Student Research Collaborator, Princeton, NJ – US.

Aug 2017 - Mar 2022 Federal University of Rio Grande do Sul, PhD in Computer Science, Porto Alegre, RS (Expected) Brazil.

Jan 2014 - Dec 2014 University of Maryland, Study Abroad, Brazil Scientific Mobility Program, College Park, MD - US.

Mar 2011 - Dec 2016 Federal University of Rio Grande do Sul, BSc in Computer Science, Porto Alegre, RS Brazil.

Awards & Recognition

IBM PhD Fellowship Award. 2020

 For academic excellence and expertise in pioneering research areas, including artificial intelligence, data science, and security.

Research Experience

Aug 2017 - Current Networks Lab, Federal University of Rio Grande do Sul, Doctoral Researcher, Porto Alegre, RS - Brazil.

- Worked under the supervision of Prof. Lisandro Z. Granville and Prof. Ronaldo A. Ferreira, researching network management topics, including Machine Learning applied to networking and Intent-based networking.
- O Developed an affinity metric for Virtualized Network Functions, to identify and prevent performance degradation and resource contention in virtualized Service Function Chains.
- Constructed a refinement method for network intents expressed as natural language enabling operators to deploy network configurations using a conversational interface.
- Researched and examined the credibility of existing Machine Learning approaches to networking problems, and security in particular, using eXplainable Artificial Intelligence techniques.

Sep 2019 – Jul 2020

Systems Lab, Princeton University, Doctoral Researcher, Princeton, NJ – US.

- O Worked under the supervision of Prof. Jennifer Rexford and Dr. Walter Willinger, from NIKSUN Inc., researching network profiling techniques and traffic behavior models in programmable data plane networks, using the P4 language.
- Developed Proof-of-concept application for NIKSUN Inc. that applies Natural Language Processing techniques to querying performance and security related reports. Integrated PoC into existing NIKSUN's product.

- Aug 2012 May 2013 Networks Lab, Federal University of Rio Grande do Sul, Undergraduate Researcher, Porto Alegre, RS - Brazil.
 - Worked under the supervision of, then, PhD student Cristiano B. Both, in a joint project with company Datacom Inc., researching on using artificial intelligence to generate alarms for network operators.
 - Developed a switch monitoring web platform using Java, and the Vaadin web framework.
- Aug 2011 Aug 2012
- Networks Lab, Federal University of Rio Grande do Sul, Undergraduate Researcher, Porto Alegre, RS – Brazil.
- Worked under the supervision of, then, PhD student Oscar M. Caicedo, researching on management on virtualized network using Mashup applications.
- Investigated network virtualization background and related works on the research topic.

Employment History

May 2018 - Sep 2019

Brazilian Computer Society, Project Manager, Porto Alegre, RS - Brazil.

- Acted as Project Manager of a 6-person development team, coordinating the development of a Journal and Events Management System (JEMS), with support for peer-reviewing submissions.
- o Defined the architecture and system technologies, having the backend developed as Restful APIs, using Django Rest Framework, and the frontend developed with Angular 7. Also defined DevOps pipeline for continuous integration and deployment using GitLab CI.
- Coordinated the tasks of the team members, providing technical support and knowledge to aid the growth of team members and the developing process.

May 2015 - Sep 2017 ADP, LLC., Software Developer, Porto Alegre, RS - Brazil.

- Developed Java application to deploy ADP's database information for the government project eSocial, using Spring and SOAP web services.
- Acted as Software Architect on agile Discovery Teams, alongside a Development Leader and a Senior Product Owner, carrying out a leadership position in the development process.
- Worked with several different Scrum teams, supporting the development of designed solutions, both in Progress 4GL and Java.
- Worked closely with infrastructure teams, both in Brazil and Chile, to configure and manage execution environments of developed applications.

Research Publications

Peer-Reviewed Conference Papers

- o A. S. Jacobs, R. J. Pfitscher, R. H. Ribeiro, R. A. Ferreira, L. Z. Granville, W. Willinger, S. G. Rao, "Hey, Lumi! Using Natural Language for Intent-Based Network Management", In 2021 USENIX Annual Technical Conference (USENIX ATC 21), pages 625-639, Virtual Conference (2021).
- o M. F. Franco, B. Rodrigues, E. J. Scheid, A. S. Jacobs, C. Killer, L. Z. Granville, B. Stiller, "SecBot: a Business-Driven Conversational Agent for Cybersecurity Planning and Management", In 2020 16th International Conference on Network and Service Management (CNSM), pages 1-7, Izmir, Turkey (2020).
- o R. Parizotto, L. Castanheira, R. H. Ribeiro, L. Zembruzki, A. S. Jacobs, L. Z. Granville, A. E. Schaeffer-Filho, "ShadowFS: Speeding-up Data Plane Monitoring and Telemetry using P4", In 2020 IEEE International Conference on Communications (ICC)), pages 1-6, Virtual Conference (2020).
- o L. Zembruzki, A. S. Jacobs, G. S. Landtreter, L. Z. Granville, G. C. M. Moura, "dnstracker: Measuring Centralization of DNS Infrastructure in the Wild", In 2020 International Conference on Advanced Information Networking and Applications (AINA), pages 871–882, Caserta, Italy (2020).
- o M. V. B. da Silva, A. A. P. de Carvalho, A. S. Jacobs, R. J. Pfitscher, L. Z. Granville, "Sample Selection

- Search to Predict Elephant Flows in IXP Programmable Networks", In 2020 International Conference on Advanced Information Networking and Applications (AINA), pages 357–368, Caserta, Italy (2020).
- R. H. Ribeiro, <u>A. S. Jacobs</u>, R. Parizotto, L. Zembruzki, A. E. Schaeffer-Filho, L. Z. Granville, "A Bottom-Up Approach for Extracting Network Intents", In 2020 International Conference on Advanced Information Networking and Applications (AINA), pages 858-870, Caserta, Italy (2020).
- M. V. B. da Silva, <u>A. S. Jacobs</u>, R. J. Pfitscher, L. Z. Granville, "IDEAFIX: Identifying Elephant Flows in P4-Based IXP Networks", In 2018 IEEE Global Communications Conference (GLOBECOM), pages 1-6, Abu Dhabi, United Arab Emirates (2018).
- A. S. Jacobs, R. J. Pfitscher, R. L. dos Santos, M. F. Franco, E. J. Scheid and L. Z. Granville, "Artificial Neural Network Model to Predict Affinity for Virtual Network Functions", In 2018 IFIP/IEEE Network Operations and Management Symposium (NOMS), pages 1-9, Taipei, Taiwan (2018).
- R. J. Pfitscher, E. J. Scheid, <u>A. S. Jacobs</u>, M. F. Franco, R. L. dos Santos, A. E. Schaeffer-Filho and L. Z. Granville, "A Model for Quantifying Performance Degradation in Virtual Network Function Service Chains", In 2018 IFIP/IEEE Network Operations and Management Symposium (NOMS), pages 1-9, Taipei, Taiwan (2018).
- A. S. Jacobs, R. L. dos Santos, M. F. Franco, E. J. Scheid, R. J. Pfitscher and L. Z. Granville, "Affinity measurement for NFV-enabled networks: A criteria-based approach", In 2017 IFIP/IEEE Symposium on Integrated Network and Service Management (IM), pages 125-133, Lisbon, Portugal (2017).

Peer-reviewed Journal Articles

- R. J. Pfitscher, <u>A. S. Jacobs</u>, L. Zembruzki, R. L. dos Santos, E. J. Scheid, M. F. Franco, A. E. Schaeffer-Filho and L. Z. Granville, "Guiltiness: A Practical Approach for Quantifying Virtual Network Functions Performance", In *Computer Networks*, Volume 161, pages 14 31 (2019).
- <u>A. S. Jacobs</u>, R. J. Pfitscher, R. A. Ferreira and L. Z. Granville, "Refining Network Intents for Self-driving Networks", In *ACM SIGCOMM Computer Communication Review*, Volume 48 Issue 5, pages 55 63 (2018).
- o O. M. C. Rendon, C. R. P. dos Santos, <u>A. S. Jacobs</u> and L. Z. Granville, "Monitoring Virtual Nodes using mashups", In *Computer Networks*, Volume 64, pages 55 70 (2014).

Posters, Workshops and Others

- A. S. Jacobs, R. J. Pfitscher, R. H. Ribeiro, R. A. Ferreira, L. Z. Granville, S. G. Rao, "Deploying Natural Language Intents with Lumi", In ACM SIGCOMM 2019 Conference Posters and Demos, pages 82-84, Beijing, China (2019).
- A. S. Jacobs, R. J. Pfitscher, R. A. Ferreira, L. Z. Granville, "Refining Network Intents for Self-driving Networks", In ACM SIGCOMM 2018 Workshop on Self-Driving Networks (SelfDN 2018), pages 15-21, Budapest, Hungary (2018).
- A. S. Jacobs, R. L. dos Santos, M. F. Franco, E. J. Scheid, R. J. Pfitscher, L. Z. Granville, "AMNESiA: Affinity measurement platform for NFV-enabled networks", In 2017 IFIP/IEEE Symposium on Integrated Network and Service Management (IM), pages 899-900, Lisbon, Portugal (2017).

Technical skills

- Programming Languages: JavaScript, Python, Java, C#, C++, C and Progress 4GL.
- **▼ Tools, Frameworks and Technologies:** Spring and Django; Node.js, React, Angular and Vue; Ionic; AWS;
- Machine Learning and NLP: Scikit-learn, Tensorflow, Keras, PyTorch; Dialogflow, SpacyNLP and RasaNLP.
- Databases: Firebase, MongoDB, S3, ElasticSearch, MySQL, Oracle and Progress.

Language skills

Portuguese: native.

English: fluent.

Spanish: advanced.

German: basic.

References

Lisandro Zambenedetti Granville

- Full Professor of Computer Science
- **m** Federal University of Rio Grande do Sul

- **▲** Daniel Braga Becker
- Chief Technology Officer (CTO)
- **m** Health ID LAB
- ${\color{red} \, \, \, } \, \, danielbragabecker@gmail.com$